Eugene C. Worman Research Material on William H. Bartlett
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Eugene C. Worman research material on William H. Bartlett
1835-1995
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Eugene C. Worman
4.1 linear feet
The Eugene C. Worman research material on William H. Bartlett measures 4.1 linear feet and dates from 1835-1995. The collection reflects Worman’s interest in Bartlett’s career as an illustrator, and includes material on Bartlett's work and travels, his publisher, George C. Virtue, and the museums and institutions in which his artwork is represented. Records include biographical material, correspondence, notes, writings, articles, printed material, reproductions, photographs, slides, and transparencies.
Biographical Note
Print collector, Eugene C. Worman, was born in 1915. Worman's interest in illustrator Willian H. Bartlett (1809-1854), led him to compile research material in preparation of a study to date and authenticate Bartlett's prints. Bartlett, a British artist, primarily known as an illustrator of commercially popular travel books, apprenticed with British art historian and draftsman John Britton (1771-1857). His work was published by major London publisher of books and periodicals, Virtue and Company, owned and founded by George C. Virtue (1793?-1869). Bartlett's work was published in several of the company's periodicals including American Scenery.
Scope and Content Note
The Eugene C. Worman research material on William H. Bartlett measures 4.1 linear feet and dates from 1835-1995. The collection reflects Worman’s interest in Bartlett’s career as an illustrator, and includes material on Bartlett's work and travels, his publisher, George C. Virtue, and the museums and institutions in which Bartlett's artwork is represented. Records include biographical material, correspondence, notes, drafts of Worman's writings, printed material including some rare reproductions of Bartlett prints, photographs, slides, and transparencies.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series based primarily on material type. Each series is arranged in either chronological or alphabetical order.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1984-1995, undated (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Research Files, 1844-1995, undated (Boxes 1-3, OV 5; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1986-1995, undated (Boxes 3-4; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1835-1995, undated (Box 4, OV 5; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 5: Slides, photographs, transparencies, 1995, undated (Box 4, OV 5; 0.4 linear feet)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Bartlett, William Henry, 1809-1854; Virtue, George, 1793-1868
Subjects-Topical:
Book industries and trade -- United States; Illustrators -- Great Britain
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Slides (photographs)
Provenance
The Eugene C. Worman research material on William H. Bartlett was donated to the Archives in 1997 by Paul Worman.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1984-1995, undated, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear ft.)
  This series contains correspondence, primarily with Michael Virtue, great-great grandson of George Virtue, and also with libraries, publishers, collectors, art institutions, colleges and museums. Letters document historic information about business transactions, Bartlett's personal travels and his relationship with Virtue and Company.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1984-1995, undated, (6 folders) (Box 1)
- Research Files, 1845-1995, undated, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3, OV 5; 2.3 linear ft.)
  This series contains research files on Bartlett and George Virtue as well as a card file on engravers from the 19th Century. These cards contain names, dates and addresses compiled by Worman's colleague, Foster Rice.
  Research files on Bartlett include biographical information, correspondence, hand-written notes about Bartlett's engravings, publishing information, printed material, published articles, writings and information about Bartlett's travels in America, Canada and Europe, as well as information about printers, plates, dating and publications. Most material document's Worman's attempts to determine the legitimacy of the Bartlett prints in circulation.
  Research files on George Virtue include extensive notes, printed material, published articles, and correspondence on the history of the Virtue publishing company, as well as biographical information on the Virtue family. Also included is the correspondence of Mrs. Charles P. Burr, granddaughter of the American painter John W. Casilear. Material concerning information on Bartlett's prints, his working relationship with the Virtue publishing company, photographs and original printed pages of Bartlett's work is also included.
  These files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Research Files on William H. Bartlett (Box 1)
    - American Scenery and the Dating of its Bartlett Prints, 1987-1988, 1994, undated (Box 1)
    - American Scenery, 1844, 1973, 1982-1988, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Bartlett Chronology, undated (Box 1)
    - Bartlett's Earliest Work, 1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Bartlett Influence, undated (Box 1)
    - Bartlett/Virtue Letters, undated, (photocopies) (Box 1)
    - Boston City Directory, undated (Box 1)
    - Canadian Scenery, 1988, undated (Box 1)
    - Canada Trip, 1993, undated (Box 1)
    - Chronology, In the footsteps of Our Lord, undated (Box 1)
    - Clive Burden, undated (Box 1)
    - Currier and Ives Project, 1993-1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Drawing Sale, 1855, 1992-1993, undated, (2 folders; see also OV 5) (Box 1)
    - England Trip, Notes, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - A. M. Hind, 1910 (Box 2)
    - Notes, Various, undated (Box 2)
    - Toronto Directory, undated (Box 2)
    - N. P. Willis, William H. Bartlett, Travels, 1986, undated (Box 2)
    - N. P. Willis, General, undated (Box 2)
  - Research Files, Bartlett Collections (Box 2)
    - American Scenery, undated (Box 2)
    - Boston Museum of Fine Arts, undated (Box 2)
    - British Museum, undated (Box 2)
    - Christies and National Art Library, 1992, undated (Box 2)
    - Minet Library, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
    - National Archives of Canada, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
    - New York Historical Society, undated (Box 2)
    - Princeton University, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Ross Collection, 1993, undated (Box 2)
    - Searight Collection, undated (Box 2)
    - University of Guelph (Ontario, Canada), 1993-1994, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Victoria & Albert Museum, undated (Box 2)
    - Yale British Art Center, undated (Box 2)
  - Research Files on George Virtue (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Casilear Family Genealogy, 1933-1967, undated, (See also OV 5) (Box 2)
    - England, 1987-1992, undated (Box 2)
    - Family Genealogy, 1991, undated (Box 2)
    - Family History, James Sprent Virtue, 1990-1993, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Simon Fisher and John Rogers, 1992-1993, undated (Box 2)
    - Illustrations, circa 1800's, undated (Box 2)
    - Last Will and Testament, Death and Burial Certificate, undated (Box 2)
    - New York, 1985-1987, 1991, 1993, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - New York Illustrations, 1845, 1856-1878, 1985, undated (Box 3)
    - Notes, Various, undated (Box 3)
    - Passenger Arrival Lists, Various, 1909, 1995, undated (Box 3)
    - Portland, ME branch office, 1990-1991, undated (Box 3)
    - Virtue Book Advertisements, undated (Box 3)
  - Research Files, Index Cards, undated (Box 3)
  - Research Files on William H. Bartlett (Box OV 5)
    - Drawing Sale 1855, Auction Catalog, 1994, (photocopy) (Box OV 5)
  - Research Files, George Virtue (Box OV 5)
    - Casilear Family Genealogy, undated (Box OV 5)
- Writings, 1986-1995, undated, Series 3:; (Boxes 3-4; 0.5 linear ft.)
  Writings include drafts and final drafts of material published by Worman. The writings deal primarily with the identification and dating of Bartlett prints, the majority published by the Virtue Company. Other writings deal with George Virtue and his publishing company, and Bartlett's influences, travels and exhibitions. Also included is a bibliography of Worman's publications.
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  - "American Scenery" and the Dating of its "Bartlett Prints", Drafts and Final Draft, 1986-1987, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - William Henry Bartlett's Earliest Book Illustrations (1825-1828), Corrected Draft, undated (Box 3)
  - W. H. Bartlett's Influence on American Book and Magazine Illustration, 1992 (Box 3)
  - William H. Bartlett's Travels in Canada-1838, Draft, 1989 (Box 3)
  - William H. Bartlett's Travels in the United States (1836-1837), Final Draft, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Booksellers and Print Collectors – A Symbiotic Relation, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Early Exhibitions of W. H. Bartlett's Art (1826-1833), Final Text, 1995 (Box 4)
  - The Guelph University Collection, 1994 (Box 4)
  - The Last W. H. Bartlett Prints to be Published, 1994 (Box 4)
  - London Publisher George Virtue's Canadian Connections in the 19th Century, 1987 (Box 4)
  - George "Little" Virtue and his Adventures with the Virtue Publishing Company in America (1852-1894), 1987 (Box 4)
  - George "Little" Virtue and the Boston, Massachusetts, and Toronto, Ontario Branch Offices of the Virtue Publishing Company of London, England (1855-1894), 1987, undated (Box 4)
  - George Virtue's Earliest Publications (1820-1833), 1993 (Box 4)
  - George Virtue and the "Numbers Business", 1987 (Box 4)
  - Bibliography of Publications, undated (Box 4)
- Printed Material, 1835-1995, undated, Series 4:; (Box 4, OV 5; 0.4 linear ft.)
  This series includes articles and writings published by Worman in journals and weekly publications. Of special note are rare original published Bartlett prints presented as loose pages, typically separated from their original published formats.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Book, Catalogue, 1869-1870, undated (Box 4)
  - Graham's Magazine, 1842 (Box 4)
  - Publications and Journals, Articles by Worman, 1987-1995, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Publications and Journals, Miscellaneous, 1968, 1983, undated, (See also OV 5) (Box 4)
  - Reproductions, 1835-1888, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Reproductions, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Reproduction, Portrait Engraving, 1839 (Box 4)
  - Publications and Journals, Miscellaneous, undated (Box OV 5)
- Slides, Photographs and Transparencies, 1995, undated, Series 5:; (Box 4, OV 5; 0.4 linear ft.)
  Most of the slides, photographs and transparencies found in this series are of engravings of Bartlett's artwork. These reproductions were used for articles, lectures, meetings and research. The series also includes some hand-written notes.
  - Photographs, American Scenery Article, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs, Bartlett Exhibition Article, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs, Illustrations for Lecture, AHPCS meeting, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, Illustrations for Lecture, undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs, Transparencies, Bartlett's Earliest Engraved Views (Britton, John, Architectural Antiquities of Great Britain, Vol. 5, 18), undated (Box 4)
  - Photographs, Transparencies, Canadian Scenery, undated (Box 4)
  - Slides, Bartlett's Prints and Various, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Photographs, Illustrations for a Lecture, undated (Box OV 5)